Guide to the Victor Oscar Freeburg Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Victor Oscar Freeburg papers
1905-1949
MS 223
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(3 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, short writings, notes, memorabilia and printed matter. The correspondence is largely made up of letters commenting on Freeburg's writings on Elizabethan drama and Hesselius. Other writings relate to ciphers and codes. Also in the papers is a scrapbook containing memorabilia of Freeburg's years at Yale together with a play entitled Sunset, produced at Yale in 1908 and acted in by Sinclair Lewis. A second scrapbook (1905-1913) reflects Freeburg's early career teaching at the U.S. Naval Academy, the College of the City of New York and contains copies of his writings and speeches.
Freeburg, Victor Oscar, 1882-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. V. O. Freeburg, 1953.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Victor Oscar Freeburg papers consist of short writings, notes, memorabilia, and other papers. There is a small amount of correspondence, which falls into three groups: four letters of 1915 congratulating Freeburg on his book, Disguise Plots in Elizabethan Drama; three letters of 1921 concerning Freeburg's unrealized plans for a round-the-world cruise for writers and artists (a diary and memorabilia relating to this planned cruise are also included in the collection); and a longer sequence of letters with Freeburg's replies, 1938-1949, concerning his research on the Colonial painter Gustavus Hesselius (1682-1755). Among Freeburg's writings is an article on Hesselius, accompanied by research notes, an exhibition catalogue and photographs of Hesselius's works, and a copy of Hesselius's will.
Several other of Freeburg's writings concern ciphers and codes. Related to these are nine glass lantern slides showing pictures and tables of ciphers from the Renaissance through the nineteenth century. These slides are in box 3. Also among the writings is the play "Sunset," produced at Yale in 1908 and acted in by Sinclair Lewis. The text is accompanied by memorabilia; other items related to the play are included in a scrapbook which covers the years 1905-1913. The contents of the scrapbook cover Freeburg's years at Yale, the U.S. Naval Academy, and the College of the City of New York, as well as his early publications and public speaking engagements.
The remaining items in the collection are a logbook from the Torpedo Training School which Freeburg attended during his service in World War I containing notes and pencil drawings of machinery; and notes and notebooks on such varied subjects as sociology, Swedish poetry, and geographical allusions in English poetry.
These papers were donated to Yale University in 1953 by Mrs. Victor Oscar Freeburg.
Biographical / Historical
Victor Oscar Freeburg, writer, painter, and teacher, taught English at the United States Naval Academy from 1906-1907. From 1908-1913, he was an instructor of public speaking at the College of the City of New York. Freeburg was an instructor of English at Haverford College from 1913-1915 and at Columbia from 1915-1916. He edited the Swedish-American Trade Journal from 1919-1922 and was a writer on the staff of the Milbank Memorial Fund from 1931-1936. In addition to his teaching and writing, Freeburg was a painter of portraits and landscapes.
Ciphers; Literature -- History and criticism; World War, 1914-1918; Scrapbooks; Educators; Freeburg, Victor Oscar, 1882-; Granville, William Anthony, 1863-1943; Gummere, Francis Barton, 1855-1919; Hesselius, Gustavus, 1682-1755; Leach, Henry Goddard, 1880-1970; Lee, Sidney, Sir, 1859-1926; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1905; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1915, 1921, 1938-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Writings
    - "Recollections of Camp Irving", 1908 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Sunset"
      - Ms and tms versions, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Memorabilia, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "A Bibliography of Physiologus and the Bestiaries", 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Secret Writing", 1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Gustaf Hesselius"
      - Ms and tms versions, [1937?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Notes, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Exhibition catalogue and photographs of paintings, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Photostatic copy of G. W.'s will, 1755 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Ciphers and Literary Men", 1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "New York of Many Names", undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook, 1905-1913 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Torpedo logbook, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Diary and other papers related to "A Voyage of Poetic Adventure", 1921 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Notes on Sociology, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Notebooks
    - Swedish poems, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Index of Geographical Allusions in English Poets, M. M. Lorentz, Columbia University", undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lantern slides, undated (Box 3)